Ricketts mss. III, 1856-1979 LMC 1831
Lilly Library
- Medieval Fragments and Illuminations
  - 46. Illumination, undated; 3 fragments, vellum (Box 29)
    Cut out along the lines of the design. In colors of blue, red, green and gold. Bird and animal, ending in scroll and leaves - 15 x 13 cm. Lion, ending in scroll of leaves - 18 cm. Goat and man, ending in a scroll of leaves - 11.5 x 3 cm. Verso blank on all
  - 47. Initial H, undated; 1 fragment, vellum. 19 x 17 cm (Box 29)
    In pink against blue with decoration ending in green dragon head. Cut from work with musical notation
  - 48. Initial H, undated; 1 fragment, vellum. 19.5 x 4/8 cm (Box 29)
    In gray against blue with red, white and gold, and green dragon head. Cut from work with musical notation. Acquired from Rappaport, Rome
  - 49. Initials, A, B, D, T (2), undated; 5 fragments, vellum. 6.5/9.5 x 4.3/6.5 cm (Box 29)
    In blue and red with looped penwork ending in animal, bird, or human faces. Cut from work with musical notation
  - 50. Unidentified medieval fragment G, 13th century; 1 fragment, vellum. 11 x 4.5 cm (Box 29)
    Italian. Liturgical text. Accompanied by descriptive note
  - 51. "Nos Nicolaus Trono...", ca. 1473; 1 fragment, vellum. 8.5 x 14.5 cm (Box 29)
    Certificate cut from longer presentation. Reversed N of gold against floral background. Date pencilled in. Nicolas Trono, 1397-1473, doge of Venice (Espasa Calpe 64: 1015; British Museum 241:673; Mansell--no reference). Latin
  - 52. Unidentified medieval leaf A, undated; leaf 3, vellum. 14.5 x 9.4 cm (Box 29)
    Religious text. Two small illuminated initials in blue, red, and gold. French
  - 53. Bible, 1250; 12 leaves, paper. 18 x 13 cm (Box 29)
    Numbers 19-21; Ezekiel 42-44; Luke 4-23; Acts 1-2; Apocalypse 20-22. Initial P in gold and pink with faces of 5 men on recto of Acts. Red and blue penwork initials. Luke 11 mended with thread. Two columns, 52 lines. Date given at end of Apocalypse. Latin
  - 54. Missale?, undated; 1 leaf, vellum. 9.5 x 7 cm (Box 29)
    Initial D in red against gold with blue, green and red decoration. Latin
  - 55. Psalms 21-23, undated; 1 leaf, vellum. 19.8 x 11 cm (Box 29)
    Two large gold initial D's; small gold, red, and blue initials. Eight lines only of 23rd Psalm. Latin
  - 56. Bible readings: Luke and John, undated; 4 leaves, vellum. 7.2 x 4.7 cm (Box 29)
    Luke 1:31-38; John 1:8-14; and two unidentified readings, one with small red, blue and gold ornament. Latin
  - 57. Illuminated capitals, etc., 16th century; 16 leaves, paper. 37 x 26 cm (Box 50)
    Album of borders, initials, and text: bound in 3/4 leather with marbleized boards
    Borders, 12; initials, 15; text, 1 leaf, unidentified
    Leaves 7 and 14 of borders may be from same manuscript with bear, birds, butterfly, lion, and rabbit. Leaf 14, blank. Leaf 15 of religious text, formerly used as bookbinding with sewing threads still attached
    Twenty-eight pieces mounted on 16 leaves
  - 58. Certificate granting dispensation to marry, 1574, May 5; 1 leaf, vellum. 29.5 x 39.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Dispensation to marry despite relationship to Vicentius and Theodorina of Albingana in southern Italy. Done at Rome. Initial scrolls and flourishes. Written in two hands. Latin
  - 59. Missale, 13th century; 1 leaf, vellum. 37 x 27 cm (Folio 1)
    Two columns, 32 lines. Red and blue initials, center marginal scroll. Later note in French dated 2 Aoust 1652. Accompanied by dealer description. Latin
  - 60. Graduale, undated; Leaves 27, 41 (fragment), 65 (fragment), vellum (Folio 1)
    Alternate leaf numbers may be 22, 26, and no number. 38 x 26 cm; 38 x 20 cm; 23 x 11.7 cm respectively. Red and blue initials; black and yellow initials
  - 61. Antiphone, 14th century; 1 leaf, vellum. 35 x 28 cm (Folio 1)
    For Pentecost: Dom. 10-11-12. Red and blue initials. Date derived from pencilled information
  - 62. Breviary?, undated; 2 leaves, vellum. 39 x 29 cm (Folio 1)
    Initials in blue and red. Latin
  - 63. Missale?, undated; Leaves 34, 76, 77, vellum. 67 x 40 cm (Folio 1)
    Initial M, 7 x 7.5 cm, illuminated in red, green, and orange against gold with additional flourishes in green, orange, beige, and gold in margin. Other initials in red and blue penwork. Latin
  - 64. Missale?, undated; 1 leaf, vellum. 53 x 37 cm (Folio 1)
    25 initials in red and blue paperwork. Latin
  - 65. Choirbook, undated; Leaves 110, 115, 116, vellum. 60 x 36.5 and 60 x 42.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Leaf 110 has been trimmed on one side. Alternate leaf numbers: no number, 117 and 118. Initials in red and blue penwork
  - 66. Choirbook, 15th century; Leaves 83 and 90. 53 x 41.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Alternate page numbers in Arabic 19, 20 and 33, 34. Large initial G, in pink against blue, floriated, on recto of 82. Large initial M historiated with two men and books in panels from haloes to sandals, in pink against blue; sandals appear to have been drawn at a later date, verso of 90. Acquired from P. M. Barnard in 1915. Accompanied by description
  - 67. Graduale, 15th century; Leaves 37 and 95, vellum. 52.5 x 37 cm (Folio 1)
    Large initial G, 10 cm., in blue against red and green penwork, verso of leaf 37. Initial G, 5 cm, in blue against red and green penwork, and initial A, 5 cm, in red against red and blue penwork on verso of leaf 95. Acquired from LeClerc, Paris, in 1907; from D. L. Passavant, Penna., 1925. Accompanied by description
  - 68A. Graduale, undated; Pages 21, 22, 39, 40, 163, 164, 181, 182, vellum. 53 x 37.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Elongated initial P, historiated with figure of man and scroll, in pink and gray against blue, 15 cm, page 21. Small initial L, 3.5 cm, with figure of man, in pink against blue, and initial M, 2.5 cm, in pink against blue, page 163. Historiated initial H with figure of woman on horse and man (Mary and Joseph?) in orange against blue on page 164. Acquired from P. M. Barnard in 1915 [lb] From the same work as 68B
  - 68B. Graduale, undated; Pages 205, 206, 219, 220, vellum. 20.5 x 37.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Four small historiated initials. Large initial M in pink against blue of Jesus teaching the disciples. Other initials in red and blue penwork [lb]. From the same work as 68A having had more trimmed from the bottom of the pages than A
  - 69. Graduale, 15th century; Leaf 93, vellum. 44.5 x 31.5 cm (Folio 1)
    Initial L in red against blue with pink ornamentation. Other initials in red and blue. Acquired from Tregaskis in 1922. Accompanied by description. Italian
  - 70. Antiphone, 15th century; Leaves 274 and 277, vellum. 50 x 36 cm (Folio 1)
    14 large initials in red, blue, black with penwork decoration. Acquired from Rosenbach, Philadelphia, in 1924. Accompanied by description. Flemish
  - 71. Graduale, 15th century; Leaf 202, vellum. 29.5 x 40 cm (Folio 1)
    Large initial S, 14 cm, in red, blue, purple, green, decorated with a deer and an eagle. Two other initials in red and blue penwork. Formerly in Forrer Collection, No. 447; acquired from Von Scherling or L. Rosenbach. Accompanied by description. Flemish
  - 72. Missale?, undated; Leaf 142, vellum. 60 x 44 cm (Folio 1)
    Two columns, 18 lines. Thirteen initials in red and blue penwork with pointed ornamentation above and below the initial. Acquired from an Antiquary Shop, Rome, 1911. Latin
  - 73. Missale?, undated; 1 leaf, vellum. 59.5 x 44 cm (Folio 1)
    Two columns, 18 lines. Large initial I in red and blue penwork and 9 smaller initials in similar style, all with circular ornamentation above and below the initials. Acquired from an Antiquary Shop, Rome, 1911. Latin
  - 74. Kabbalistic Amulet, undated; 1 leaf, vellum. 22.7 x 17 cm (Folio 3)
    Information given on verso. Hebrew
  - 75. Prayers for the States General of Holland and the Magistrate of the City of Rotterdam, 17/18th century; 1 leaf, vellum. 29 x 24 cm (Box 29)
    Prayer said in the Spanish and Portuguese Synagogue of Rotterdam. Information given on verso. Hebrew
  - 76. Miniature of woman dressing her hair, undated; 1 leaf, paper. 20 x 13 cm (Box 29)
    Against a border of orange and blue with silver colored, red, yellow, and white lines, 31 x 22 cm. One attendant holds mirror, another waves fan. Five line inscription across the top. Verso, blank. (Rajastan, 18th century?)
  - 77. Miniature of man riding a deer, undated; 1 leaf, paper. 9.8 x 9 cm (Box 29)
    With floral border, all in colors of orange, red, green, gray, black, gold, and blue, 14 x 11 cm. Verso, blank. (Rajastan, 18th century?)
  - 78. Lettre de Vigiazamjam a M le Gouverneur recu le 16e janvier 1757, 1757, January 16; 1 leaf, paper. 32 x 20.5 cm (Box 29)
    Official correspondence, text in an Indian language, on gold-leaved design paper. Governor of India at this time was Robert Clive, 1725-1774. The Black Hole of Calcutta occurred June 20, 1756
  - 79. Unidentified Indian leaf A, 17th century; 1 leaf, paper. 15.5 x 10 cm (Box 29)
    Against gold and blue wide floral border, 32.5 x 22 cm. Verso blank except for date pencilled in. (Rajastan?)
  - 80. Shahnama (Book of Kings), 16th century?; 1 leaf, paper. 32.5 x 19 cm (Box 30)
    Miniature of the ruler on his throne with seven figures approaching. Inscription above and below the miniature. Colors of blue, gold, orange, red, yellow and black. Text on verso. (Title information from Thomas Lentz, 9/82)
  - 81. Koran, 1761?; 1 leaf, paper. 11.5 x 19.5 cm (Box 30)
    Thuluth script? Gold-bordered text, blue and gold floral decoration on page 18.5 x 26.7 cm. Leaf from calligraphic album. Date derived from note on verso. (Title information from Thomas Lentz, 9/82)
  - 82. Leaf from Laylī va Majnūn, 19th century?; June 29, 1814 AD; [the night ahead of Thursday] Wednesday 11 Rajab 1229 AH; February 7, 1858 AD; The night of 22 Jumādī al-Thānī 1274 AH; Niẓāmī Ganjavī, 1140 or 1141-1202 or 1203; 1 leaf, paper. 23.3 x 15 cm (Box 30)
    The incipit page of Laylī va Majnūn by Ilyās bin Yūsuf Niẓāmī Ganjawī
    Four columns of text. Decorated with illuminated sarlawḥ in gold, blue, red, black, and white. Accompanied by dealer description
    Nastaʿlīq script in less than intermediate (mutawassiṭ) quality
    Sharafa foliates.
    An illuminated piece (lawḥah).
    A headpiece (sarlawḥ) containing a gilded basmalah in Eastern Kufic script in mushajjar foliated design with a katībah and ṭurrah (edge) at the top.
    One turanj (mandorla) in middle and two half turanj in both sides. Between mandorlas are islīmī foliates and within the mandorlas are khatāyī foliates.
    Margins (ḥāshiyah) in girih shape around the basmalah in a long mandorla in lapis lazuli containing golden islīmī foliates within a chain shape ṭurrah (edge) at the top and bottom.
    Gold and black text frames (jadwal-kashī).
  - 83. Leaf from Haft Awrang: Silsilat al-Dhahab: Book Two, c. 1800-1850?; Jāmī, 1414-1492; 1 leaf, paper. 23.5 x 11 cm (Box 30)
    The incipit page of Haft Awrang: Silsilat al-Dhahab: Book Two by Nūr al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān Jāmī
    Text in four columns with portions in red on page 30.5 x 17.7 cm. Illuminated sarlawḥ in gold, blue, red, black and white. Nasta'līq script.
    Nastaʿlīq script in maximal (ustād) quality. The writing style of the letters nūn and yaʾ says that the calligrapher is from late Zand or early to mid Qājār area.
    An illuminated piece (lawḥah) in maximal quality.
    A headpiece (sarlawḥ) containing a katībah with a red title in Naskh script within a gilded mandorla in lapis lazuli background surrounded by four khatāyī and two Shāhʿabbāsī foliate flowers. within three chain ṭurrah(edge). The main ṭurrah (edge) is inlaid like (shibh-i muraṣṣa').
    Another designed katībah with soot background and a ṭurrah (edge) and a double square frame (jadwal-kashī) at the top.
    At the bottom the following page title in red ink and Naskh script in intermediate (mutawassiṭ) quality.
  - 84. Leaf from Haft Awrang: Tuḥfat al-aḥrār, undated; Jāmī, 1414-1492; 1 leaf, paper. 23.7 x 11 cm (Box 30)
    Text in one and 4 columns on page 30.5 x 17.7 cm. Illuminated sarlouh (without text) in gold, red, blue, green and black. Nastaʿlīq script
    The incipit page of Haft Awrang: Tuḥfat al-aḥrār by Nūr al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān Jāmī
    The incipit page of Haft Awrang: Tuḥfat al-aḥrār
    Nastaʿlīq script with shikasti-yi taḥrīr characteristics in intermediate quality.
    A headpiece (sarlawḥ) in poor quality and seems to be patched later to the page contains a gilded central mandorla (turanj) that has been made of an islīmī foliate frame and has been surrounded by a blue background mandorla. Two half-mandorlas with shāhʿabbāsī foliate flowers inside, are in both sides.
  - 85. Leaf from Haft Awrang: Subḥat al-abrār, undated; Jāmī, 1414-1492; 1 leaf, paper. 20 x 11 cm (Box 30)
    Text in one and 4 columns on page 30 x 17 cm. Illuminated sarlawḥ in gold, red, blue. Nastaʿlīq script.
    The incipit page of Haft Awrang: Subḥat al-abrār
    Nastaʿlīq script in good, close to advanced (Mumtaz,)quality.
    A headpiece (sarlawḥ) contains a gilded central mandorla (turanj) that has been made of an islīmī foliate frame and has been surrounded by a blue background mandorla which has lachak like shape in corners. Two sar-turanj(head mandorla), with khatāyī leaves and flowers foliates inside, are in both sides of the central turanj.
    Gold and black text frames (jadwal-kashī)
    At the bottom the following page title in red ink and Naskh script.
  - 86. An example of calligraphic collage., undated; Muḥammad Shafīq al-Sayfī; 1 leaf, paper. 15.2 x 21.7 cm (Box 30)
    Mounted on board-"tablet"-lawḥa) with a Calligraphic collage (muraqqaʿ) work in jujube with afshān (flecks of gold) on paper. Two sayings(ḥadīth) of the Prophet of Islam. 1- (In Thuluth script at the top) "He who is content with his food (or earnings) is independent of mankind." 2- (In Naskh script at the bottom) Five are the people who are not in need and are still allowed to have interest in religious donations and charities: • Those who fight with the enemies of God • Those who works for them. • Slaves or the one that has bought them. • One that has a poor neighbor and wants to pass the donation or charity to the poor, however, the poor returns that as a gift to the one. • and it is said too about "who has lost his money while traveling." [to these, I the calligrapher, profess] 3- (In Naskh script at the bottom a note from the calligrapher) I, Muḥammad Shafīq al-Sayfī, wrote this following Uthmān Ḥafiẓ's style. God forgive both of us. Left: A lachak decoration with khatāyī leaves and flower foliates. Right: A gilded paper collage work with islīmī and khatāyī foliates.
  - 87. Drawing: Persian woman preparing food, undated; 1 leaf, paper. 10 x 9 cm (Box 29)
    Mounted on board 25.3 x 6.3 cm. Brown ink sketch filled in with subdued colors of beige, brown, orange, green and blue. Arabic inscription over head of woman. Numbered 713 on verso
  - 88. Seraphinus, Master General of O.P. (Dominicans). Petition concerning the mysteries of the Rosery, 1622, May 10; 1 leaf, vellum. 49.6 x 66.5 cm (Folio 2)
    Written and ornamented by Marcus Antonius Raymund [Secretus?]. Decorated in red, blue, green, orange and aluminum color with ovals depicting two men, a coat of arms, and a devotional scene to Mary. Signed by Seraphinus. Seal missing. Latin. Given at Rome. Rta. Folio 130
  - 89. Unidentified Dutch? document, 1746, June 1; 1 leaf, vellum. 34.5 x 52 cm (Folio 2)
    Written and decorated in black ink: tulip, carnation, sunflower, and others. Signature in another hand: Rofe Otten Loman. Seal missing
  - 90. Jno. Gartley. Receipt to Jacob Graff for schooling for his son John, 1772, January 20; 1 leaf, paper. 9 x 18.2 cm (Box 29)
  - 91. Anna (Hibbard) Bolley, 1771-?, schoolteacher. Penmanship sample, 1788; 1 leaf, paper. 12.15 cm (Box 29)
    In black ink. Information on verso in pencil giving family background of sample
  - 93. Henry Bristow. Receipt to Charles Graff for purchase of stationery and Instructions in the New and Improved System of Writing, 1829, January; 1 leaf, paper. 15 x 11.5 cm (Box 29)
    In black ink. Endorsed on verso
  - 96. Initials, undated; 12 leaves (Box 29)
    In ink with gray wash, designs of figures, flowers, creatures and scrolls, on paper mounted on heavy stock. Accompanied by note in ink which reads: Original. A - 15 x 15.9 cm. B - 14.4 x 15.3 cm. C - 15.5 x 13.2 cm. D - 14.6 x 15.3 cm. E - 14.6 x 13 cm. F - 15 x 15 cm. G - 14.5 x 14.8 cm. H - 15 x 15.7 cm. I - 15.1 x 11.3 cm. L - 15.2 x 15 cm. M - 14.5 x 14.5 cm. R - 15 x 15.4 cm
  - 97. Initials - A, a, G (2), I, N (2), O, P, S, T, undated; 10 fragments, vellum. 6/12 x 4/6.7 cm (Box 29)
    Cut from work with musical notation. Penwork in red and blue ink. Initial I on verso has floral decoration in blue, green, red, and gold
  - 98. Initials - A, B, D, E, H, L?, R, S, V, U, undated; 10 fragments, vellum. 8/9 x 6/9 cm (Box 29)
    Cut from work with musical notation. Angular style lettering in eroded black, blue and yellow
  - 99. Initials, undated (Folio 2)
    U - in green leaves with pink floral center against gold background. Cut from Maccabees, 14 x 10.5 cm. Initial size: 5.1 x 5 cm. D - in green against pink background. Cut from Galatian; 20 x 15 cm. Initial size: 3 x 3 cm. Both hand colored. Both cut from German Bible printed by Koburger at Nurnberg in 1483, as identified by 2 accompanying notes
  - 100. Binding only - metal binding with religious subjects, undated; 15.3 x 18.5 cm (Folio 4)
    Scrollwork with floral decoration. Front cover embossed with Crucifixion, three soldiers, horse's head, five other figures or heads, two cherubs, blank cartouche below. Back cover embossed with Ressurrection, three soldiers, heads of three other figures, one angel, two cherubs, blank cartouche below. On spine: Jonah emerging from the mouth of the whale. Single clasp with open work. No date, no place, no maker. No information on acquisition but bears sale no. 308. For comparison see Nos. 26, 29, 43 in Sotheby's Catalogue, London: Silver and Enamel Binding, 10 May 1985 (Lilly Z999 .S7)
- Miscellaneous
  - "Miscellany" (Box 36)
    An assortment of miscellaneous items including the empty holder for a group of letters of G. A. Cumberland (William Augustus, 1st Duke of Cumberland, 1721-1765), the cover for the Souvenir of Port Sunlight, 1891, and other pieces
  - Framed nameplate for Lindsay Ricketts: "Scribe Illuminator Binder" (Box 54)